<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Alexander Whillas - Solid</title><link href="http://alexander.whillas.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://alexander.whillas.com/feeds/solid.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://alexander.whillas.com/</id><updated>2023-05-28T00:00:00+12:00</updated><entry><title>Solid Pod Server</title><link href="http://alexander.whillas.com/solid-pod-server.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-05-28T00:00:00+12:00</published><updated>2023-05-28T00:00:00+12:00</updated><author><name>Alexander Whillas</name></author><id>tag:alexander.whillas.com,2023-05-28:/solid-pod-server.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Trying to get behind the linked data movement by following Tim Berners-Lee&amp;rsquo;s latest crazy vision of the future of the web.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://solidproject.org/"&gt;Solid&lt;/a&gt; is an attempt at making standards for returning control over your data, getting it out of the big tech silos. You run your own content server called a Solid Pod that you keep all your data in and control access to third party web apps to via OAuth2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Some background&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tim Berners-Lee started the Solid Project which is a lose collection of standards, still in its infancy after more than a decade, which defines Solid Pod Servers, which are an online identity for you, described in Turtle/RDF and a place to keep your public and private data. The&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The idea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was thinking this might take off more if it was easy to deploy a personal solid server on a cloud provider where storage is cheap and you could use lambda/cloud functions to do the serving i.e. your not paying for them when they are not being used. Uses OAuth2 as authentication and the server is just a web server so all the components are already available as Rust crates, just have to bring it together. I&amp;rsquo;ve also seen some examples of using &lt;a href="https://github.com/nogibjj/rust-mlops-template/tree/main/lambdathreads"&gt;Rust for AWS lambda functions&lt;/a&gt; and apparently is much cheaper because of the speedup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Persistent storage on the cheap?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The OAuth2 server needs to some persistent state to track the sessions and their details. Persistent state can be expensive in cloud as databases are not cheap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DynamoDB on AWS is &lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/free/database/?p=ft&amp;amp;z=subnav&amp;amp;loc=3"&gt;aways free&lt;/a&gt; under a certain amount (which it should be). There are &lt;a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/sdk-for-rust/latest/dg/rust_dynamodb_code_examples.html"&gt;Rust examples&lt;/a&gt;. Does force vendor lock in to AWS :( There are &lt;a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/sdk-for-rust/latest/dg/rust_dynamodb_code_examples.html"&gt;examples using the Rust SDK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AWS &lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/simpledb/"&gt;SimpleDB&lt;/a&gt;: Amazon SimpleDB is a highly available NoSQL data store that offloads the work of database administration. 25 SimpleDB Machine Hours and 1 GB of Storage for free each month. Sadlt there are no examples online for using SimpleDB and rust :(&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep a SQLite file in a bucket and load it for every request? Vendor agnostic but might be slow?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Rust"></category></entry></feed>